once the matter data it's all three of
these links to the same place
and just former them for different ways
if you're is working on something it's
okay to commit and you can just feel
free to write me a summary that this
isn't really important
and just go ahead
page
someone else was out in the page
that's okay
this system is designed to work with
most will be politically got wikipedia
when you have don't our world being able
to edited document
someone else might have it
what they've done is gone shown that
someone else wrote those
answers my text
acknowledged copy does
save
packages uni
and say sorry i'm a reading which you
wrote
so they go look at the history
we should see that
excellent someone else i did it
that's okay
that's great don't feel bad that you
were editing the page that's good
by padding has got a system you can go
and see the changes happen you can then
merged the two together and collaborate
self
if you happen it's a on something it
at parks issuing is grumpy it just means
that you can't do lunch to work too much
to to get it
what any other further questions on wiki
answered now we can keep coming back to
you throughout the semester if you start
drinking at your things with
the wiki page
feel free to do if you talk about it
more as we go
it's just that it's a tool for us to
collaborate
and we can use it however works best for
us
yet
if you want to do the map something like
that
so what you can do
we just said
maps dot google dot com
if the at that website gives you an
embedded link of some sort
so i think if you just do link
you can we get in
i'm not sure they have a non
polyethylene that'd suit intake embedded
link
and as long as the wiki software doesn't
walked us
making his head
and you can pay site in there
hopefully the wiki won't
walk it
check for you
uh...
it looks like it's probable up here
so sometimes they'll take stuff
and either you have to fiddle with a
format to prevent the wiki engine from
changing that interpreting in some way
so here it looks like
it's ignored iframe which is an html tag
and so is that is linked to this
page in there
this map
and it's it's fiddle with it so that it
doesn't work that means that we have to
go in and read uh... menu on how to
invent actually shitty now without
having that the wiki engine fiddle with
it
me take a little bit of work to figure
out how to do that
all xd
it's called
over it so that
there's a browser plug-in for its
firefox clint all tax that lets you as
spent
or
editing in here it is always all of the
challenge
there's one big confirm the wiki page if
you write a lot of stuff
in the wiki
save often
because if you hit the back key or the
browser closes
any save written for an hour
that's gone
writing something else and paste in or
save fairly often or uses all taxed
allen attacks every you trust a little
bit more than the browser
a definite lost some fancy events that
took some time
detoured copyright in which the
internally not really
if their son is really restricted in
someone's really hates and you know any
might
you worry about inside
preferring to give a fair use in the
academic environment
if this is an outside page
and they're easier than you would really
want to worry about
copyright
so if you look at wikipedia they're very
careful about their image is that
they're all fair use
so in people in our which are using it
for how weather is involved in the
copyright law
stuff issues internally for course
we've never had any trouble
demos time
massive realize that the spell my last
name which is
kind of a pain
there's a version of this in the class
notes and there's also
a blog post about processing some data
and making a graph
so my blog is issue vp colon slash slash
choi error
s_ c_ h_ w_t_ h_r_
dot org
slash wont
if you don't call me let me get some
german company that does something i
don't think it
but not me
so let me give you guys in a sense of
what we're getting into
grill look at a lot of command stated
themselves don't look like they do much
teaching you had a copy of new files
kinda feels like t_v_ steps
and you michael
frustrating wonder why in the world were
bothered with this
so i think if you are really nice real
world sample of
using the stuff we're going to be
we're learning
and show you
viewed by combining all these things
together you get are really powerful
system that lets you
look at manipulate them
and uh... analyzed data
so i did
would we have a weather station upon the
roof
that uh... in in a cloud ben smith i
myself have been working on and i want
to see
what happened with hurricane
i'm gonna go ahead
keep this up here and i'm gonna go start
which is here
aram login to researchers
editing images can be mirrored by this
on this issue if u commands
and you're welcome to fall on a few if
you can't
so according to research tools
and vista bites the weather station on
the roof
is actually
broadcasting is data over the internal
network if you connect to it
there's a couple of a kind of
connections this one is yes you have to
connect up to the store
and after the data other ones
will broadcast out their data and you
just listen for this so we want to
connect to the server
and listen to it
and the commands
is called so pat
it's a network kaptur that basically
passes data from any port to someplace
else or back-and-forth
i'm a ask it
to go and collect up
to uh... was called p_c_p_ transmission
control protocol
if it's going to the internet
follicular computer
and send that they are
to the consul
will get into all the details of
housework but
it'll just keep saying it to us forever
so i want to see the first few lines is
a little unix command called ahead
that will only grabbed the first time
lines of taxes and stop
now one thing to note here
if you've got an injury phone arrived
bones from mike that the tools don't
really play together very well you can
take the data from
one application
sent to the next one an impostor third
wanted to ask them to all work together
unix and one except
are exactly the opposite and really want
you to work together between tools
so retake this tool called so capital
called head
seconded editor and and that
taking a look at what's on weather
station so five
join here
and paste
quite a bit so cat
and i say pcp for colin
deal longer ones that are computer and
also i think inside ccom
it's on port thirty six thousand
and learn more about the stuff as we go
two dash says put the standard out zero
little conventions you learn about don't
feel like you have to know them right
now
and head
but do that
a wet ketchup the server
and showed us some data
it's all encoded
but i know what it says but at least we
have some data
and why
to going to figure out how the state of
works
and start doing some graphs of the
weather station
those data is in a format called
there is a doctor i went in here
opinion when you know
a guy named eric raymond has written
extensive documentation that's open
because if you want to rebuild actual
pocket issue for you made up a time for
our or something like that
official reference but this is good
enough for most purposes
a coaster explains each of the message
is that what i play are
and you're gonna see these in your
records is there's one called saying i
peaceful t_g_a_
and do you know al these are
positioning messages that come out of
g_p_s_ is
and we want the weather station data
coming out of our weather and so it's
putting out
some g_p_s_ information because the
g_p_s_ in weather station
and politician is meant for being on a
ship
so there's things like heading
and uh... motion
we don't care about those but we want to
get
the weather data
the weather station simply go back to
them
there's a message called
w andy
and dat
these are whether statements
says the data about the weather
it's it's in color is kind of a pain
abdullah library that will deco does
and we also know which ones are
available
here's a command
call to grab that will see you later on
does pattern matching in text so we can
say
remove anything missus me saying remove
all comments from the the file
so there's a little funny language to to
specify things like comments
cut cuts things into pieces i want to
cut out the first statements book
before the common suddenly tell it
i'd like to break it apart of the comma
which is unfortunately hiding behind
this extra taxes here
sort is a command of sorts things and
dash you flag on it says unique
we'll get into it
actually running these and see you get a
sense of how to use them and had asked
for help on these instructions
and without all the meanest rings they
were found in that
this file so this is the at
about wildfire all
and got into it pro apart
and i've listed all the miss trains that
are available and that file so i'd go
look them up
and then figured out that i'd like to
look at this point
how white you will fight on programs
that pulls it apart
and pipe on there's a way to split
things on a common
single and sample of doing that
i've written this library calls
neema dot
bernie mac decode
veggie codes nema statements in a few
akdphi new students are having used to
have to add the names
bring some type of a does that
and if you decode whole message like
that will actually go and grab
that wind parcel out and returned you a
little bit of
icon that actually says what's in there
from there
i were a little bit a pipe bomb won't go
into a pit just
looser the file
finds everything that's called
and dat
if it's andy eight saves the idea and
stars building up a little database of
the pressure
the speed of the timestamps
and then use that will call
i typed on with the so often called high
lab
which we use a lot of this semester
and this is a tool that's designed for
building fox is very much like the
matlab plotting
in fact it's using applauding package
called map plot leaden
and then went through
process all the data
made a raise of things to build applaud
you can use the basic statistics that i
could ask at the minimum and maximum
values of the speed
so here it's a nightmare for second so
zero two twelve point four meters per
second
you can ask it done minimum maximize of
the pressure
and in alberta that speed
so we thought there was one point five
years per second during these three days
and playing with
don't worry about the details here will
get into
all of them and you become pretty
familiar with how to be able to use all
the spring quickly
here the commands of everyone matlab is
a look very much like now i have a more
walk through how to build fought
how to make multiple figures
how titled on how to create special axes
they're labeled by date and time
he can get really fancy
the best part is
here's a picture that came out of the
program syrup
india and you can see her caring coming
through
there's the yuki seeding time coming
through here
uni hear me say again again sized issued
always being you can see if he is local
time around here
for size do you have a very upset
because the statue of ships
and driving all over the globe
who knows what kinds of hearing
there's nothing like getting data from
somewhere in the globe
and sometimes own and nobody look down
which one
so you can see
three days of data above hurricane the
pressure on the roof
just over one
and then as the storm king three can see
the low come true in come pick back up
and you can see the winds p come along
and you can see that it was
fairly consistently slow you get some
little bits when coming through
and you can see that the range
of the speeds was pretty high so it's
very gusty winds
appear on the roof
now we have come about
bab location for a weather station or if
it's right down in the trees
at least a great way taz in day to see
and it used to think that sentence on a
ship
so if you go on a research vessel this
is exactly what you might do when you
show up to a new ship
maybe they've got a weather center may
be the date is not really terribly well
available on the shipping you want to
see what's going on
you want to buy the new sensor banquet
sandy sensor on the roof they put the
network
put on the network
you can then pick up to that sensor and
start making plus the data
right away
from the beginning of the idea right in
the library and they can apply it to be
two or three hours dot identified on for
a long time
i think it would take longer
when you're starting out
but it doesn't take forever
if i were doesn't came out saying see
apparently is a lot
i'd still be working on it two weeks
later
it's not crazy sometimes of matlab to
get things right up and going
but in the long term there's a huge
amount of flexibility
and you can build plots of just about
anything you want in any style that you
want
raining towards
by the end of semester you should be
able to make lots like this
all-time without too much stress
and be able to use these kinds of things
in your other classes so if you start
seeing
uh... nema data from g_p_s_ is in
geology
then he showed no problem being able to
parse that data plot ups and look at
whether g_p_s_ was doing
if i've done my job right
dealing with things like g_p_s_ is
should be no no problem you'll be
focusing mostly on the theory of the
g_p_s_ rather in the highlight parse
that
that darn line coming out of the g_p_s_
so i should give you guys a sense of
what we're aiming for and some of the
types of tools that we're going to
expect that most of what you saw going
by it
didn't make sense that's okay
we're gonna go back and we're gonna
start picking up piece-by-piece
and building up the tools you need to be
able to do stuff like this really easily
what you guys bring up putting
did get a store nearby bought it for
branch dot
it's that coding and other stuff
kind clothes that
and for today
i've done a pretty good job i hope
building up some basic instructions
and the class website that'll show you
each the steps that we're going to run
the spots
racism very basic stuff with
that shallow and moving files around
learning how to
to get help on commands
something universal machine today so you
guys could take a virtual machine with
you
haven't fully finished setting up a need
to create an account
free login to an abortion machines on
thursday
all show you a link that you can
download a file to your laptop
or you can see at home
and
any other computers running out
vmware player tool
and you can run one x on that computer
in a window
this'll give you guys the chance to play
with this anywhere you want
is lvds accent software they were using
in class here
so when you use this outside of class
you always have access to even if you're
not in this classroom
or if you're not secom network
phyllis jump to the basic command-line
section
the go-ahead login
and i wanted to be on
on the shelves so you can see what's
going on try as we go we're going to go
ahead and create a bunch of stuff and
see
what's possible
in the class notes
i've got
more tax the talks about wire you
learning bashed
uh... why we choose vast versus a
different shelters other shells
you can go to readers right now you can
take it as dash
in my take is the batch of the using
lots of people disagree with you know
it's okay
there's some notes on the bugging
and what's do you think its stock
and we show you one thing real quick
which is
the control c character
is often
written a couple of her ways but they
see a pull down the control p
any press seat
that's the break or like stop what i'm
doing kind of command
in michelle
let's also britain sometimes
c
or
the character of a call that the up at
and then a c
those i mean
pull down the ctrl key pressie and
that's the like i want out of here
doesn't always work with us
most often the other way to get out
you can also try sometimes took just a
letter to you if you're in a program
that's booking i could take input
sometimes cues the way to get out
will see that it's not the same across
programs
which is a bummer so you have to learn
bland you know each of these works and
why new you'll start getting a sense of
it after a while
so i'm gonna walk through almost exactly
what's in the notes
so feel free to have the notes up next
to us
in britain to basically the where are my
one of my flicking act
section so were underneath managing
files
which would be
managing files were here
so you can tap into a back through this
on your own
tried all again
and see where you get
deftly doesn't hurt to try it sees a few
times
so the first time in the show you guys
is sick
p di v d print working directory
and this is the
where my commands
if you forget how do these feel free
to shout out mass or asked on the ir c
channel
diskeeper asking until you get
comfortable with these things soapy
obedience print
working
directory
so this is when you look changed
locations like in windows if you're
switching our folders
this is the current folder directory to
children
if you want to make
a directory
we can
to u_n_
and k
g_i_ or
soulmate directory
example
and it doesn't complain to you
then
probably worked
and if you want to go into that
directory
we can go into these important cd
and could you print looking to record
excellent appear the commands
and k do you know i r
directory
performers
cv
is change directory
now that's all great that you had to
know if they're so
how do we see what's in our current
location
that's the ls or list of commands
if you just return steel
it can be kind of disconcerting because
i cal awsome
it just came back with the next prop
saying
that actually means there's nothing in
this directory
mentioned it briefly before last time
command fake options and they typically
have a dash
for the option
there's a few programs adult followers
but this is the majority programs
dash a means all
socialist all
hard to see
but over here there's a dot
and two dots
ls
is list
files
to special directories
there's a period going to put it
circle around either cc there's a period
there
that's your current
directory
and it's a little weird
you might think that you don't need to
know where you are right now be able to
say this card refuted sometimes you do
need to be able to say
right here
into a period does dekhkar directory
and two periods
bull smiley face in their which really
confusing
two periods
the parent
directory
and this was for refer to as up
if you have a tree
like you're home free
there are any fat
it we've created sample
and sore now
an example
and this is
to the home directory which is
in this case i think it's uh... slash
slapstick on
and each and then you use your name
knowing that
dash away
gives you all
and the dot files are typically hidden
if you are no more about them
you can do
along with sting dash l
and that's going to give you
those permission bits we talked about
what time was just art
to get to know
didi on the left means directory
the rest of the ring or for now
as who owns the file sony
what group i'm in
from a user
and
this would be
the file size was kind of weird to think
the directors have a file size that they
need to keep track of stuff on their own
and then
one it was last modified
just a few minutes ago
so let's use that special directory
called talk dot to go back up
out of the example directory so cv dot
dot
anarchy
and now you're back to your home
directory
and the home directory
in unix inlex
is a special character called mathilde
or the squiggle
if there's a couple other names for it
but it's uh...
it looks like that's a cool wave
can see below that the wave
that's called mathilde
and that's your home
directory
now that's to be different for each one
of you
everybody's got their own home rectory
so in your login that till it is your
home directory
you can also say
so that i know username
so if you want to look at my directory
you could do an ls
filled out and my name but that are in
the end
and i'll give you my home directory
so would you guys go ahead and take a
from the notes
take a look at my home directory do an
ls
dash l_a_
filled up
if it really goes far my last name
and by the way to take a seat in a town
it will complete my last name for you
see always remember two or three
characters in my lifetime
there's lots of tricks
winx that will let you
speed through things only have to
remember
and typed a minimal amount of stuff
specially on the trail and here we are
taking the and less typing is better
so if you do now especially
sew this where
you're gonna get all kinds of junk
because i actually was working on costs
and there's a few
those written here they can actually
colorized things and
i cannot read those colors
certain bostic our special white bread
other ones get white and some
directories get blue
feels the cert seeing these patterns
and i'll help you kinda get a sense of
things
if you open this up like this flooring
classes and even though i know you can
always ask me if i haven't mentioned it
doubts this shelter that for me ls did
that without me asking
you can turn it off
but i don't remember the option to do
that
when they did
darkness a later you cannot always try
to ask
each command for help
and they often have a dash dash help
option
sometimes that's not
very helpful because there's just a lot
of junk
ls has lots and lots of options
so you can usually
do something like
ls
dash dash
that works for of commands
some of them have special options that
are not that for help
but that's the you know anything trying
we do get most walkway
when you're working with the shell you
oftentimes wanna see stuff without
actually doing anything
there's a nice commands
called echo
they'd just prince to terminal
so this is where you can try stuff and
say i want to see what you're going to
do
but please don't do it by giving then
delete files and you want to try out the
command first to see what it might be
doing
you give that way
so if we want to see the till the
character
it's a echoed back but where the safe
for first hello
and it right out
hello world
first traditional computer science first
program that you right
sophie type echo hello world you've
written the traditional computer science
global program
extremely boring
delegates a echo till the that home
directory
plan to enter
it's been told the path to my home
directory and expand that till the
to wherever that points
every single one of you will
will have a different home directory
based on that so if you wanted and try
it
different usernames
you can take that out
pgi
for example
if you start taking any character it
it will go and try to complete that if
you hit tab
tha tab is the complete character
for most commands
suspect had to you on the left hand side
usually about caps lock
it doesn't always work isn't always
something that can figure out for you
but if you use a kit silva
the letter g_ isn't george
you can then
hit tab ill give you an option
if we typed
g_-eight for example have have again
it guarantees one unique thing
scanner
lookin
games users
so there's actually unless there's a
whole bunch of usernames become with the
system that are used for
operator some type of background stuff
so gains
outlets have lots of gain support if
you're
borden c
answers are addr tree
that's owned by the user games that
manages
gamestop
if you want to say look inside of it
of the directors from someone else
for example you want a look at my
example directory
you can say ls
sober
choi air
swatches a separate ur between
directories in windows
you'll see this slash
the slash that leans left
an athletics
we always use this large bid means right
which is next year shift key on american
keyboards
so we create this example directory so
you can say ls
filled up my last name
slash
example
and should see director with nothing
and we can also come back
echo
and you'll see
it had echo till the end
my usernames flash
example
you'll then see that expands out for
this long path
so that's the way that you can try to
see what's going on with the command of
his acting weird
you can use this that the blood what's
going on
the other thing to note is if you or
typing commands
you can always hit the apparel
and cycle back three-year-old commands
they keep their history file
there might not be very much in the
worst yet
but you know they'll have over time
you can use those for help
the thing you can do is if you work in
sanford weill you want to see the
process even going through
there is a great command called
it's going to tell you about
what's going on in the past
typist jury
it keeps a record of every command you
typed in the session
and you can go back through that and use
that as documentation so that might
behavior figuring something out they
might take
in ten twenty thirty forty tries to
figure out the command that you want to
use
this history what's been going on is
safe here for you when you can use that
to the liquor documentation sometimes
it's just too much we're trying to
figure something out
to write down every command that you're
going to be using their own and some of
them you'd breakdown scratched out right
down scratched out
and this way
you can go through work on stuff
type history and it's got a clear record
of exactly what she typed
so up here you can see on line sixty six
that was where
i tried out logging-in type
trekking up to the weather server
and the sting out the weather there
now record if i wanted to write a
documentation on that
it depends on how
it's set up
on most links machines a default is to
save your history
you know after you log out
the trouble timmy is sometimes if you
have two shells open that you can login
most will find something server had two
shells
and through split your process and
mentally between the two
and only one of those first to write the
final remarks
there's also ways to set the maximum
number of
commands that it will keep
so it may reset
and loans old ones after certain time
painter settings
since i'm not right-click
when you're in terminal specially in
this one with buddy
the mouse has nothing to do what saved
on the server
so this is a command run on the server
and if you right click
we start doing things with
the party shall you're talking about
scroll back like to talk about saving
the sessions then
copying such a clipboard
that doesn't interact with what's going
on in the shall
so that history was talking to the bass
on server
so if you want to save the whole session
in the responses comes back
you want a copy that from padi
that suffered from whites the bash l me
so it doesn't know what you're doing
inside of the window to control the
window itself
allah knows is that
you've got a windows so big
and
it's got a history things that uh...
it's done surface or fiddling with the
scroll back at how much you can get this
it doesn't know anything about that
but my sense so is typically best
disorder think like a mouse doesn't
exist when you're looking for stuff
if it's a lot of it used to that
in the mouse defusing for pasting and
copying text but
after that just let it go for a while
if you've been doing wonderful on time
trying to take a while to get
comfortable with that
them
there's
occurs
that's a good point will be doing this
morning on the road
is that there's all kinds of little
cheats
band i used lived by them
began a life
our fingers would go crazy train type
everything that we do
there's ways to search
for all commands
i can say like so cat
and i can do a search
and it was indifferent
shell so doesn't remember that one but i
could say ako
so if i take echo i can go back
anniversary for milwaukee through those
a little bit later on
there's all kinds of ways to to work
with the children story and stuff
it's really amazing the number of things
you can do
you can learn a new thing every day for
the rest realize that you would not and
i think storm within the cells
the escalation point and the history
number is an excellent one
there's also if you want to run the
watchmen again there's two estimation
points
and we'll come back to these guys
throughout the semester
on each of these machines there
there may be all kinds of discs mount on
your list which means you may have
attach stories like the greater rains or
network drive things like that
and you are no
how it'd no what's available on your
system
it can be a little confusing if a driver
attached you mean to where it is
and there's a command
called t f
it prints out the disks that are mounted
and of course is going to give you more
information than you want
because some of those tix are real
they're part of the operating system
keeping track of things
it's really very fine machine
so here's one debit essay jam
that some shared memory thingy that you
should carry
nothing about
there's a command
stories that period that seem kind of
useless before peace a_t_f_
and dont
that means gimme
that this information for the disk in it
that contains this directory so were my
right now
right here
tell me about the disk that i'm in
fifty f dot
and this tells you a little bit more
interesting information about what's up
so we're looking down here
it's not on
slash home so that's where we are for
your pvd
it's are you'll see a slash home in here
it's can't say that uh... decides
and says one killed by blocks so there
here's a lot of one killed by plots
here's how much is usually or some other
number of its kind of hard to understand
here is how much available
we have a as a class at least two
percent of the homeless
so it means we got from the space to
play with
in terms of what we're doing is we have
a release are filling up
but is that a lot for a little
so we want it
habit human readable form
c_d_f_
dash h asks for human readable
and dot
and you can now see
that the size of change two gigabytes of
megabytes so here we have
a twenty-two gigabyte disk which
practitioners as priests fall
we'll try to keep the server small
were thinking about
just using for the class it's not really
available for processing huge
blocks of data
but it's enough that we can load in
test data sets and try out stuff
we've used three hundred and thirty four
megabytes between all of us
which is by fish dinner almost nothing
and we have twenty-one gigabytes
available
chains that too narrow
and d_f_
dash h
period
that's human
readable
disk space
down the road
we're gonna be drowning discs on this
machine for you guys to use it and will
be doing
was called absentee
which is the windows file share so will
be nodding when this file serves on to
this that you guys can work with
and you'll see those show up with a d_f_
so i said
we've no amount of some drive for you
with the date on it
uh... you used the f_ commanding figure
out where
rebecca got mad computer
actually was a commands
but i haven't talked to anything about
how to go and find help on their own
and if i didn't do that that's kinda
cool
there's a a lot of information on the
system
everyone xbox comes with a ton of
documentation
referral windows background is not the
way you normally think of
there may be a help system but here
we're looking at terminal
there's a couple waves that
traditionally in terminal leave ask for
help
the first one
is called man
and a m
you may hear
if you ask for help someone says the
word to you
uh... dfm
and be member choreographer guys
redefine manual and you can replace the
applecare favorite at ford
that's not necessarily if someone tells
you work if m it's not necessarily mean
it saying
the docking station should be able to
help you and please read that first
before you come back and ask me again
archiplanet said nicely most the time
i've had said to me which is always good
so what we can do is really taking his
commands that we've types
and we can ask for the manual on that
program so if we see in india
you're gonna get some information about
d_f_
main pages or
a great resource
they're written by all sorts of people
of various writing skills
and various backgrounds
they may assume
more knowledge than you have
they made
being complete they may be horribly
written by non-english speakers
that's okay it's a it's about the fact
is the first turning point
you know cool as always available to you
to but if you're on the turmoil
specially for etsy this docking station
goes view with sea if you get used to
reading it style
we'll start being able to figure stuff
out
you're inside it something here
if you just to enter it's a state of the
next lines here stuck inside of some
program
and they have i think all the pager
and inside the pager
you can use the air appease you can use
it enter the next pages
states
to go forward
but the key thing is if you want to put
on that
tight heal
kiefer qua an allegation out of the
rampage
i'd ever seen plenty of people who are
serving out the one man
but no one teaches them keel and they
get very very frustrated at the end of
closing their shelf
and it sucks
took you is the quick
you can hit space
to go forward the space part
if the keyboard separate you be easier
refused to go up and down
if you look at here you see
a lot of information right now
a lot friendlier mad dash dash help
goes through
and talk of the options if you're lucky
sometimes they'll have examples in there
not always
though also have see also other programs
that might be related to that but you
might be interested in
the author we can blame for the software
these nice people read it
how to report bugs if there's problems
for the software
level reasonable exist so there is that
everybody contributes back
so even if you are not
a programmer you can still contribute
back his projects you can send them
toward permission phase-out misspelling
or if you are
housing tax do you think you should add
to this man page
he knows people and they might actually
fifty
take your texans to get in
to not put out that and i want to find
that the man information about something
that i'm not sure about what it is seem
i got it so you know what you're looking
for exactly
may do a lot of sort something we want
to find out about sorting
you can demand
has not been called to ask a which is
also written out
apropos
which is overheard type
and we can save and swords
volume in this case alert
that's gonna search all of a man pages
the one-line descriptions of the top
beach one
for the word swords
so you might get back some funny things
you don't expect
but it might also get you the war the
command that you need to learn
so here we asked for support we got back
the whole bunch of stuff that we don't
know or care about
but that's were commands
that we just used
earlier in the sample is in there so you
can then
realize that there is
mansour is available
there's some funny numbers after this
that three in the one
commands
manuals with one after them our command
line program so you can run
things with two and three
are for c programming
and you probably in the scores are
tribution anything with it two or three
after it
is not going to help you worry much
man pages with
wanted after them
ni minutes out program you can actually
run
and there's a name pages a year going to
be interested
we have a few more minutes so let's do a
few more
unix commands
that what you work with files and start
playing with things
there's a really great tools inside the
command line
to let you work with large numbers of
files
if you have a thousand log files that
you're working with from some instrument
it's okay
eight it can be overwhelming at first
but there's really great ways to help
you
slice out pieces of what you might want
like if you want to grab just one month
of data at the father named well
it can be actually fairly easy
so we're going to a section on that
class called pattern action
so specifying groups of files pattern
matching
snowman home directory and if you ever
want to get back your home directory
just type c_b_ inhibitor
and you go home
you could also do you see the
division same spot
in here let's go ahead and create a
couple files
and i should be the touch command last
time so we'll touch
and look forward to say one final you
can actually do any number of files
touch one two three
animal henner
so now they do
along listing
you see the files one two and three
and they're all
penises touch
they're all zero length so we're just
playing with it doesn't matter what's in
them
weekend then
are on them
more done before knowing
we don't want any more
proof they're gone
uh... the scary thing about that
is there doesn't have to you
so you can with one command delete your
entire directory and all the children
underneath it and everything you've been
working on blast
ten months
and that's why i have backups
later we'll be also you had a separate
subsys permanent could you could always
out of dash hike
so we'll do it the touch me again so i'm
gonna hate
copernicus tree with the arab keys place
in the touch again
to the touch
if we do our agm dash on it
one to you and three
and our
prompt before this
touch warranty three
victory
did the touch to create three files
added the long listing to see if they're
there and there's one two and three
and then ided the arm again
but with the dash i_ in there
and it now says for each file
remove
regular actually look and say if the
empty
how true this file one company type wire
and for yes or no
so i can say yes to this one
kuwait i really don't want to hear about
file no
to number two
and yes for number three
later on it what you don't create
an alias so they hit always asks you and
you have to do
current off that feature
so that you don't actually going to
leave everything
really quickly because is a great way
over his work
all of us had to do this for a long time
invariably you will do this by accident
you won't believe that he did not want
to leave
and not to go back ups and go get it
turn out to create a whole bunch more
files
one two three four five six seven
tanzania's
was about typing
was also create
one hundred
and he will throw on an eleven
twelve and thirteen
you have a lot of files now
you know really exciting project going
on with no data in it
it's good to death a good for example
touch is a great way to play with stuff
and to learn how to work with files
without having to it
you've realty
for no reason that pattern matching
solar struck with the star
and star means match any text
ls
stark
is very much like to bring the eloquence
is ls
and any file one was in the file
be very very careful
this in a very bad idea
are aman star
from willfully things very quickly
and makes a very efficient
thrills leave before you can hit
controller close a window
they'll be gone
so start is is a match anything
this is anything
weekend match anything separates going
to go a matter directories and that's
going to go look at the great reason
get really annoying
so what we can do is start saying
what's not to anything that starts with
a one
so if we look at our list of things
we've created
there's a fair number of files to start
with one thirty c l_ s_ one-star
outcome
uh... one can hundred
eleven twelve thirteen
you can also say
what ends in a zero
so if you hands in zero
so you start
ls star and then zero
and i'll give you
battalion the hunger and
ski if you think about files that are
named with
the dates like if they had year dash
month dash day
you could ask for all the things that
were in two thousand eleven
or everything that was in august
for everything that was
the first day of every month
c_d_s are building up these pattern
matches and say i want to grab every
files the first eighteen months and just
use those
you can also start
wrapping that completely around so you
can save what starts with the one in
ends with a zero
you'll want to gassing
was to start with a one and the zero how
many files are gonna get back
blows it when we find out
ticked same thing as we just got before
but if you also said what
starts with a one day
and and for the three
will back if two thirteen
or will it not
yet because anything also means that
nothing
so if that star doesn't match anything
if you could take the one of the three
in sticking together
that that's a good match
cyst or is it was a really nice
character for finding offer to stuff you
can say
ls
now we have
let's call it a park however have won
those in my folder i can say show me all
of the tape archives or towers
sector ls
star dot tower
and there's one that came back if i had
a bunch of text files and and dot t_
extn could say
ls
star dot
t x t
i don't have any but if there were you
could enlist although so it's really
neat
if people are using extensions
to the normal convention
like if iraq somehow files and they were
all i
mean blacks and all you could let star
back somehow
there's another masters especially
helpful the will end up using up there a
bit
and that's the question mark
and that matches any
character
it's a single character defects
so the question
is any
one
character
so worry it back if we just do it how
less than a question mark
for asking the great question
it's every file but has one
characteristic
if we do to question marks
and every file that has coming this two
characters
now ministry of suspicious since i've
got some great reason you have an
example directory
if you do you
dash d on dallas
it's they're not looking to directories
the gets really annoying very quickly
so if we do ls dash do you need to
characters i had this little weather
w x that i was working with on that blog
posts
and i don't want to look and every time
i was doing
and then if we also have the dash l
went along with thing
and you can see that
we have a couple of empty files and our
weather directory
steepest are combined had to say
i want all files thirty characters long
but i want to start with a one
so that's great
or wants it depends
in three
cvs are going up these queries that maps
bits and pieces the data so few long
things smartly you can answer pulling
apart
pretty effectively
you can also do you ranges of
files so if we want a list
teacher fired
we can put a square bracket
since eighteen dash five
and now said two three four five
things like the rangers log files by
dates are becoming very easy to work
with if you name them
with numbered
so that's the square brackets carter
arrange
uh... number
dash number
that also works with characters you can
say
anything starting with eighty three j
a dash j
the gotten things to make an example
here quick
so the u_n_ allies
cash l_d_
how about and through z_
anything this first one and three z
and we get back that
disney mid deck dot taryn this w x
directory those two things
match that pattern
those kinds of we start off it
there's not very interesting
it's very hard to imagine sometimes
houck working together
but will star combining them and all
sorts of ways
and eventually other start using them
without thinking about you know start
saying well i've got a bunch of files
and scrub dispatch it will take that
action here
and peace things together
through building up a big jigsaw puzzle
and looking at the one couple pieces
they don't look like what he thinks are
putting together
let's do something really quick
animal uh... and for today
if we want to go look in the system
directories theirs
a place for binary simply save
which yeah
it soon
means type t f
that commanders in that uh... slash bin
directory if we want to go look in there
and say what what starts with z
they can say ls
flash pins flashes the star
and i will tell us all the files
in the been directory
to start with the letters the
so if you're looking for something
it can really help you start to
understand what's where help research
through
this computer which is full of all sorts
of tools
that your you'll be learning
so next time
we're going to go ahead and get
i work so machine on to all of your
computers
so you can run one x
not on the server which sexy sitting
upstairs and over in the new wing
you'll be running when it's been a
window
on your computer's andean copy that file
onto a usb drive ticket with you and use
it on a computer that has
idea more player
so these are tools that as you were
making go with you pretty much anywhere
hopefully you guys your brains haven't
gotten to century from this
we're going to go back it we're uses
commands throughout the semester
and expect that it just takes a lot of
reputation to get comfortable with them
and to learn
which ones you wanna remembers from his
commands
you have to know them all
you seem to know enough
that you can get done what you need to
get done
there was a lot of material for one day
for a beginning command-line
so hopefully
keep with it and will uh...
we'll keep goin thru room
to revert to a scene and should be a
process and they're very soon
kasich roomful of if you have any
questions or wanna talk about in the
stuff that we've gone over so far
on that you discover the underscoring
their heresy names
life
yet you have mobile login serbia the
irish teaching or it will have more for
people in the same name
so you can never stop loving for mostly
ones in the total to see that you're
already in there
that may mean create a new name it it
just depends on which program reason
what character they had to make
don't be surprised that happens